Mss.Ms.Coll.109
American Philosophical Society
- Certificates and Awards, 0.25 linear feet
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science Fifty Year Membership Certificate, 1985; 1 item (Box 102)
  - American Association of Physical Anthropologists, Darwin Award, Correspondence, 1994; 1 item (Box 102)
  - American Humanist Association Humanist of the Year Award, 1995, 1994; 1995; 2 items (Box 102)
  - Ashley Montagu Peace Award, 1996; 1 item (Box 102)
  - Association for Humanistic Psychology, Certificate of Appreciation, 1995; 1 item (Box 102)
  - Doctoral Degree, Columbia University, 1937 (Box 120)
    Item Removed to Oversize, Box 120.
    General Physical Description note
    1 item
  - Ellis Island Medal of Honor, Nomination, undated; 1 item (Box 102)
  - Honorary Citizen of New Orleans Certificates, 1967; 1978; 2 items (Box 119)
    Items removed to Oversize, Box 119
  - Honorary Degree, Ursinis College, 1972; 1 item (Box 120)
  - Marquis Who's Who Inc., Citation, 1968; 2 items (Box 102)
  - Phi Beta Kappa Association, Distinguished Service Award, 1985, 9 items (Box 102)
  - Saybrook Institute Humanistic Service Award, 1991; 6 items (Box 102)
  - University of North Carolina at Greensboro, Honorary Doctor of Science Certificate, 1987; 1 item (Box 102)
- Personal Information, 0.5 linear feet
  Series IX, Montagu’s personal information, contains a wide variety of items. From a primary school grade sheet, to his admission certificate to Columbia University, to his curriculum vitae, and even obituaries, the series spans his entire life. Also included is information regarding Montagu’s Princeton home, passports and tax documents, memorabilia from his England home and personal financial documents, among other ephemera.
  - Application for National Endowment for the Humanities Fellowship, 1978; 1 item (Box 103)
  - Biographical Information, 1979-1999; undated; 10 items (Box 103)
  - Biographical Interview with Geoffrey Lyons, July 18, 1989, 1 item (Box 103)
  - Borough of Princeton, Correspondence, 1962; 1988; 3 items (Box 103)
  - Car Accident and Insurance Information, 1988; 7 items (Box 103)
  - Columbia University Admissions Certificate, 1927; 1 item (Box 103)
  - Curriculum Vitae, undated; 2 items (Box 103)
  - England Memorabilia, 1982-1991; undated; 32 items (Box 103)
  - Family Correspondence, 1962-1991; undated; 35 items (Box 103)
  - International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences, Biographical Supplement, 1980; 1 item (Box 103)
  - Magazine and Newspaper Articles, 1941-1989; undated; 15 items (Box 103)
  - Medical Information, 1942-1998; undated; 16 items (Box 103)
  - Miscellaneous, 1938-1989; undated; 40 items (Box 103)
  - Obituaries, 1998; 3 items (Box 103)
  - Offer of Employment, Wellcome Historical Medical Museum, 1929; 1 item (Box 103)
  - Passports and Selective Service Materials, 1939-1980; 6 items (Box 103)
  - Personal Financial Charts, 1985-1989; 5 items (Box 103)
  - Primary School Grading Sheet, 1923; 1 item (Box 103)
  - Published Interviews, 1974-1989; 5 items (Box 103)
  - Sewer Line at Princeton, New Jersey Residence, 1989; 1990; 40 items (Box 103)
  - Tax Documents, 1990; 3 items (Box 103)
  - Travel and Hotel Invoices and Receipts, 1991-1995; 8 items (Box 103)
- Printed Materials, 3.0 linear feet
  Series X, the printed materials series, consists of published works and reprints authored mainly by others, but including one work by Montagu himself. Also included are bound volumes, magazines and newsletters, as well as trial transcripts from the William Shockley libel lawsuit against Cox Enterprises from 1984, for which Montagu was deposed.
  - 100 Not Out, 1927; 1 item (Box 104)
  - Abbie, A.A., A New Outlook of Physical Anthropology, 1951; 1 item (Box 104)
  - Amemiya, Tsuyoshi, ed., Learning from the Filipinos, undated; 5 items (Box 104)
  - American Association for Maternal and Child Health Inc., Maternal and Child Health, 1967; 1 item (Box 104)
  - Anatomic Chart of Adult Human Skeleton, undated; 1 item (Box 120)
  - Anatomie Humanie, undated; 2 items (Box 104)
  - Anthropological Maps, 1946; 3 items (Box 120)
    Items Removed to Oversize, Box 120.
  - Bible Light Star, 1981; 1 item (Box 104)
  - Bradford and the Inquiring Mind, 1961; 1 item (Box 104)
  - Brown University Child Behavior and Development Letter, 1986; 1 item (Box 104)
  - Bulletin of the American Professors for Peace in the Middle East, December 1975, 1 item (Box 104)
  - Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists, May 1949, 1 item (Box 104)
  - Carrier Foundation Medical Education Letter, 1988-1994; 6 items (Box 104)
  - Catalogue of an Exhibition Illustrating Prehistoric Man, 1951; 1 item (Box 104)
  - CEA: An Endorsement of Joy, undated; 1 item (Box 104)
  - The Christian Register, 1956; 1 item (Box 104)
  - Ciba Symposia, vol. 7, No. 12, March 1946, 1 item (Box 104)
  - Ciba Symposia, vol. 9, No. 11, March-April 1948, 1 item (Box 104)
  - Council for the Study of Mankind, Bulletins No.11-14, 1962; 1963; 4 items (Box 104)
  - Creation/Evolution, 1985; 1 item (Box 104)
  - Dendron News, 1991; 1 item (Box 118)
  - Dobzhansky, Theodosius and Bruce Wallace, The Problem of Adaptive Differences in Human Populations, 1954; 1 item (Box 104)
  - Dr. Chauncey D. Leake and the University of Texas Medical Branch, 1942-1955, 1 item (Box 104)
  - Dultz, Ron, 1996; 4 items (Box 104)
  - EcoLogic, 1991; 1992; 2 items (Box 104)
  - Ecopsychology Newsletter, Fall 1996, 1 item (Box 104)
  - Ecumenics International, 1994; 1998; undated; 12 items (Box 104)
  - Elvirita Lewis Foundation Newsletter, 1985; 1986; 2 items (Box 104)
  - Emergence, 1981; 1 item (Box 104)
  - Emphasis '65, 1965; 1 item (Box 104)
  - Esalen Catalog, January 1981- June 1981, 1961; 1 item (Box 104)
  - Eugenics Record Office, 1932; 3 items (Box 104)
  - Experts Questionaire, Resolved: That More Stringent Controls Should Be Imposed Upon Government Agencies Gathering Information About United States Citizens, undated; 1 item (Box 104)
  - Face to Face: an Interreligious Bulletin, 1980-1985; 3 items (Box 105)
  - The Facilitator, 1987-1992; 6 items (Box 105)
  - Family Center Report, 1990; 1 item (Box 105)
  - Family Life, vol. xxii, No. 9, September 1962, 1 item (Box 105)
  - Familyborn, 1988-1993; 8 items (Box 105)
  - Frank, Lawrence K., Human Conservation, 1943; 1 item (Box 105)
  - Free Inquiry, 1990; 1 item (Box 105)
  - Frontier Perspectives, 1995; 1 item (Box 105)
  - Gadfly, 1957; 2 items (Box 105)
  - Hammel, Harold T., Thermal and Metabolic Responses of the Alacaluf Indians to Moderate Cold Exposure, 1960; 1 item (Box 105)
  - The Global 2000 Report to the President, 1980; 1 item (Box 105)
  - Goldstein, Marcus, Demographic and Bodily Changes in Descendants of Mexican Immigrants, 1943; 1 item (Box 105)
  - Graduate Faculties Newsletter, Columbia University, June 1967, 1 item (Box 105)
  - Harper, William Rainey, The University and Democracy, 1970; 1 item (Box 105)
  - Health and Human Rights Advocate, 1996; 1997; 2 items (Box 105)
  - Homosexuality, 1953-1964; 26 items (Box 105)
    Several magazines from One and the Mattachine Review.
  - Hora, Thomas, Transcendence and Healing, 1961; 1 item (Box 105)
  - Hosken, Fran, Female Sexual Mutilations: The Facts and Proposals for Action, 1980; 1 item (Box 105)
  - Howells, W.W., Variation of External Body Form in the Individual, 1957; 1 item (Box 105)
  - Human Peace, 1988-1997; 6 items (Box 105)
  - Humor, 1980-1995; 8 items (Box 105)
  - Indian Affairs, 1967-1972; 1975; 13 items (Box 105)
  - Inquirer, Organ of the Unitarian Christianity and Free Religious Fellowship, No. 5911, October 22, 1955, 1 item (Box 105)
  - Interchange, vol. 7, No. 1, January 1978, 1 item (Box 105)
  - Intercom, 1968; 1 item (Box 105)
  - International Symposia on Circumcision, 1994; 1 item (Box 105)
  - Issues and Actions, 1969; 1 item (Box 105)
  - Junior High Newsletter, February 1963, 1 item (Box 105)
  - La Leche League News, 1960-1993; 54 items (Box 106)
  - Ladies' Literary Club Season 1953-1954, 1 item (Box 106)
  - Listener, vol. 81, No. 2088, 3 April 1969, 1 item (Box 106)
  - The Male Maternal Instinct, 1971; 1 item (Box 106)
  - McCulloch, Warren S., The Past of A Delusion, 1953; 1 item (Box 106)
  - Montagu, Ashley, et al., To Hold These Truths: Our Moral and Spiritual Resources for Brotherhood, undated; 1 item (Box 106)
  - Mothering Publications, 1988; undated; 3 items (Box 106)
  - Movius, Hallam Jr., Palaeolithic Archaeology in Southern and Eastern Asia, Exclusive of India, 1955; 1 item (Box 106)
  - Muhsam, H.V., Beduin of the Negev, 1966; 1 item (Box 106)
  - Mumford, Stephen D., The Pope and the New Apocalypse, 1986; 1 item (Box 106)
  - Muse News, 1970; 1 item (Box 106)
  - NAPSAC News, 1985; 2 items (Box 106)
  - National Association for the Advancement of Humane Education Journal, 1974; 1 item (Box 106)
  - National Committee Against Repressive Legislation (NCARL) DC Memo, 1986; 1 item (Box 106)
  - Native Americans, 1939-1967; undated; 9 items (Box 106)
  - NCDS News, 1984; 1 item (Box 106)
  - Neuro·fibroma·tosis, 1990; 1 item (Box 106)
  - New Jersey State Council on the Arts, Versatility: March 1993, 1 item (Box 106)
  - New Outlook, 1983; 1 item (Box 106)
  - Night Light, The Lucidity Institute Newsletter, 1989; 1 item (Box 106)
  - NOCIRC Newsletter, 1989-1995; 3 items (Box 106)
  - Nuclear Deception, 1993; 1 item (Box 106)
  - Oakley, Kenneth, Dating Fossil Man, 1956; 1 item (Box 107)
  - Occasional Papers of the Center of Marine Ethnology, No. 1, 1973; 1 item (Box 107)
  - Patterns of Disease, December 1960, 1 item (Box 107)
  - P.E.N. News, vol. x, No. 5, February 1964, 1 item (Box 107)
  - Pediatric Annals, 1981; 1 item (Box 107)
  - The Philadelphia Center for Research in Child Growth, undated; 1 item (Box 107)
  - Philosophical Transactions of the Royal Society of London, Series B, Vol. 223, Pp. 57-120, 1932; 1 item (Box 107)
  - Piltdown Man, 1914-1992; 18 items (Box 107)
  - Population Crisis Committee, 1985-1991; 4 items (Box 107)
  - Population Reference Bureau, Inc., 1974; 1975; undated; 3 items (Box 107)
  - Population Reference Bureau, Inc., Marriage, Divorce and Living Together, undated; 1 item (Box 107)
  - Population Reference Bureau, Inc., Population Bulletin: Marrying, Divorcing and Living Together in the U.S. Today, 1977; 1 item (Box 107)
  - Positive Ink, 1990; 1 item (Box 107)
  - The Presbyterian Outlook, 1971; 1 item (Box 107)
  - Prevent World War III, 1958; 1969; 2 items (Box 107)
  - Princeton Montessori School, Focus on Family, 1993; 1 item (Box 107)
  - Princeton Recollector, 1985; 1 item (Box 119)
    Item removed to Oversize, Box 119.
  - Proceedings of the Seventh International Congress of Phonetic Sciences, 22-28 August, 1971, 1 item (Box 107)
  - The Protestant, 1946; 1947; 3 items (Box 107)
  - Race, 1919-61; undated; 16 items (Box 107)
  - Race Relations in Human Relations, 1945; 1 item (Box 108)
  - Response Magazine, 1988-1996; 6 items (Box 108)
  - Rivers, Conrad Kent, These Black Bodies and This Sunburnt Face, 1962; 1 item (Box 108)
  - Roosevelt College Lecture and Event Schedule, Fall 1953, 1 item (Box 108)
  - Sanders, J., Inheritance of Harelip and Cleft Palate, 1934; 1 item (Box 108)
  - Science in War, 1940; 1 item (Box 108)
  - Shalom, 1969; 1970; 2 items (Box 108)
  - Shockley Trial, Transcripts, 1983; 1 item (Box 108)
  - Shockley Trial, Defense Motion for Summary Judgment, 1983; 1 item (Box 108)
  - Shockley Trial Transcripts, Montagu Witness Prep, 1983; 1 item (Box 108)
  - Shockley Trial Transcripts, Shockley Deposition, Vol. 1, 1983; 1 item (Box 108)
  - Shockley Trial Transcripts, Shockley Deposition, Vol. 2, 1983; 1 item (Box 109)
  - The Silver Bugle, 1975; 5 items (Box 109)
  - Škerlj, Božo, Vloga in Mesto Neandertalcev V Človeški Evoluciji, 1956; 1 item (Box 109)
  - Sparks into the USSR, 1957; 1 item (Box 109)
  - Stand By!, 1958; 1 item (Box 109)
  - Star Beacon, 1957; 3 items (Box 109)
  - Story of America's Oldest Museum Building, 1952; 1 item (Box 109)
  - Studies in Physical Anthropology, No. 1, 1949; 1 item (Box 109)
  - Tarrytown Letter, 1983; 1 item (Box 109)
  - Teilhard Perspective, vol. 24, No. 1, June 1991, 1 item (Box 109)
  - Terrace, H.S., et al., Project NIM Progress Report II, 1976; 1 item (Box 109)
  - Thomas Jefferson Research Center Newletters, 1974; 1979; 2 items (Box 109)
  - Truthseeker, 1989; 1990; 2 items (Box 109)
  - Turnabout: Magazine of Transvestism, 1963; 1 item (Box 109)
  - University of London, University College Magazine, undated; 1 item (Box 109)
  - The Virginian, 1956; 1 item (Box 109)
  - Voice of Reason, No. 49, Spring 1994, 1 item (Box 109)
  - War and Peace Digest, 1992-1995; 4 items (Box 109)
  - Why War? A Correspondence Between Albert Einstein and Sigmund Freud, 1939; 1 item (Box 109)
  - Женщина и Земля (Woman and Earth), 1993; 1 item (Box 109)
  - Women's International Network, undated; 3 items (Box 109)
  - World Goodwill Newsletter, 1980; 1 item (Box 109)
  - World Population News Service, Popline, vol. 5, No. 2, March 1983, 1 item (Box 109)
  - Yerkes Newsletter, 1974; 1977; 3 items (Box 109)
- Photographs, 1.5 linear feet
  Series XI consists of photographs. Included are portraits of Montagu for professional use, as well as candid snapshots of Montagu with family and friends. Also incorporated are photos taken sure Montagu’s conversations with Einstein at the latter’s Princeton, New Jersey, home, as well as various other photographs Montagu acquired through the course of his studies and teaching tenures. Series XI also contains photos removed from correspondence for conservation purposes, as well as an assortment of photographs of Montagu’s friends and acquaintances.
  - Contact Sheets and Negatives, undated; 42 items (Box 110)
  - Figures for Miscellaneous Books, undated; 200 items (Box 110)
  - Finnovation Conference, Lahti, Finland, Photos, 1970; 9 items (Box 110)
  - Miscellaneous Photos, undated; 272 items (Box 110)
    Photographs gather from throughout the Montagu collection. Does not include photos of Ashley Montagu, or his family.
  - Ashley Montagu, undated; 83 items (Box 111)
  - Ashley Montagu, undated; 132 items (Box 112)
  - Ashley Montagu with Others, Including Family, undated; 17 items (Box 112)
  - Ashley Montagu with Others, Including Family, undated; 250 items (Box 113)
  - Ashley Montagu with Others, Including Family, undated; 142 items (Box 114)
  - Montagu Family, undated; 42 items (Box 114)
  - Marjorie Montagu Car Accident, undated; 8 items (Box 114)
  - Conference on Consciousness, June 1950; 2 items (Box 114)
  - Slides, undated; 131 items (Box 114)
  - Australia, undated; 4 items (Box 115)
  - Australian Aborigines, undated; 46 items (Box 115)
  - Dolphins, undated; 6 items (Box 115)
  - Malinowski, Bronislaw, undated; 3 items (Box 115)
  - Photos From Series III, Montagu Poem, undated; 1 item (Box 115)
  - Photos From Series III, One World or None, undated; 1 item (Box 115)
  - Photos From Series III, Noise, undated; 1 item (Box 115)
  - Photos From Series III, Premaxilla (photoreproductions), undated; 12 items (Box 115)
  - Photos From Series III, Robert Nesbitt, undated; 8 items (Box 115)
  - Photos From Series III, Sequoya, undated; 1 item (Box 115)
  - Photos From Series III, Wallbrook Frontal Bone, undated; 4 items (Box 115)
  - Piltdown Man, undated; 7 items (Box 116)
  - Silver Gelatin Print of Adah Isaacs Mencken, undated; 1 item (Box 116)
    Mislabeled as a Daguerrotype.
  - Tyson, Edward, undated; 80 items (Box 116)
  - White Bushman, undated; 2 items (Box 116)
  - Circumcision, undated; 52 items (Box 116)
    Includes photos of male and female circumcisions. Please consult with Library Staff before access.
  - Oversize Photos, undated; 5 items (Box 118)
    Items include self-portraits of Fritz Warndorf, Erich Kahler(2), as well a photo of Ashley Montagu and one of Albert Einstein.
  - Oversize Edward Tyson Images, undated; 2 items (Box 118)
  - Oversize Photos of Montagu and Einstein, undated; 14 items (Box 119)
- Recordings, 0.5 linear feet
  Series XII contains audio and visual recordings of Montagu at various speaking engagements, as well as audio recordings of Montagu’s radio debates with William Shockley.
  - 60 Minutes: Too Good to be True, 9/24/95, 1995; 1 item (Box 117)
  - Ashley Montagu: Being Human in an Inhuman World, 1993; 1 item (Box 117)
  - Details of the Library Skeleton, undated; 1 item (Box 117)
  - Eleanor Robrach Tribute, undated; 1 item (Box 117)
    5 minutes- side 1 only
  - Health Watch with Janet Snow, Guest Ashley Montagu, undated; 1 item (Box 117)
  - Margaret Mead CBC Toronto Broadcast, 19 Nov 1978, 1 item (Box 117)
  - Memorial Service for May Sarton, October 7, 1995 Nelson, NH, 1 item (Box 117)
  - National Association of Nurse Massage Therapists presents Ashley Montagu, 1996; 1 item (Box 117)
  - The Optimism of Aging, undated; 1 item (Box 117)
  - PPPANA (Pre and Perinatal Psychology Association of North America), 6/31/93, 1993; 1 item (Box 117)
    Video includes a 27 minute segment featuring Ashley Montagu, a 16 minute segment featuring Diane Sherwood and a third, untimed, segment featuring "others."
  - Richard, Michel Paul, The Sociologist's Song, undated; 1 item (Box 117)
  - Schockley-Montagu Debate, 1973; 1 item (Box 117)
    Reel to reel audio tape.